Guide to the Trent Collection of Whitmaniana, 1841-1992, bulk 1845-1849, 1854-1857, and 1864-1892
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Writings Series, 1841-1944 and undated
  - Manuscript Poems Subseries, ca. 1855 and undated
    - Leaves of Grass
      - Leaves of Grass (Table of Contents, 1881-1882 edition, with instructions to the printer), Former call number: MS 19 (Volume MS 19)
      - Leaves of Grass (Autograph MS and printed pages, printer's copy for portions of 1881-1882 edition), Former call number: I-1 (Box I-1)
        - I. Inscriptions
        - II. Song of Myself (Pages 1-23)
        - II. Song of Myself (Pages 24-48)
        - II. Song of Myself (Pages 49-72)
        - III. Children of Adam
        - IV. Song of the Exposition
        - V. Song of the Redwood
        - VI. A Song for Occupations
        - VII. Birds of Passage
        - VIII. Broadway Pageant
        - IX. By Blue Ontario's Shore
        - X. Autumn Rivulets (Pages 1-26)
        - X. Autumn Rivulets (Pages 27-53)
        - XI. To Think of Time
        - XII. Whispers of Heavenly Death
        - XIII. From Noon to Starry Night
      - THE Poem (?One grand, eclipsing poem Poem of Materials) (Autograph MS, draft portions of "Starting from Paumanok" and "Mediums"), Former call number: MS 12mo 15 (Volume MS 12mo 15)
      - Outlines for a Tomb (Autograph MS, draft outline), Former call number: II-5A 17 (Box II-5A 17)
      - Pictures (Autograph MS, draft outline), Former call number: II-5A 21 (Box II-5A 21)
      - Theme for piece poem An opera (Autograph MS, draft portions of Proud Music of the Storm and The Mystic Trumpeter ), Former call number: MS q 22 (Volume MS q 22)
      - Proud Music of the Storm (Autograph MS, draft outline and corrections), Former call number: MS q 23 (Volume MS q 23)
      - Song of Myself (Autograph MS, draft portions), including Unnamed Lands, Former call number: MS q 1 (Volume MS q 1)
      - Song of Myself (Autograph MS, draft portions) To be at all - ..., Former call number: MS 2 (Volume MS 2)
      - Song of Myself (Autograph MS, draft outlines) It is no miracle now..., Former call number: MS 3 (Volume MS 3)
      - Song of Myself (Autograph MS, draft portions) Light and air!, Former call number: MS q 4 (Volume MS q 4)
      - Song of Myself (Autograph MS, draft portions) Bibles, traditions, and formulas..., Former call number: MS q 6 (Volume MS q 6)
      - Song of Myself (Autograph MS, draft portions) My Spirit sped back..., Former call number: MS q 7 (Volume MS q 7)
      - Song of Myself (Autograph MS, draft outlines) There is no word in any tongue, Former call number: II-7C 201 (Box II-7C 201)
      - Song of the Broad-Axe (Autograph MS, draft outline), Former call number: II-5A 12 (Box II-5A 12)
      - Song of the Redwood Tree (Autograph MS, draft portions), Former call number: MS 18 (Volume MS 18)
      - A Song for Occupations (Autograph MS, draft outline), Former call number: MS q 8 (Volume MS q 8)
      - A Song of Joys (Autograph MS, draft outline), Former call number: MS q 194 (Volume MS q 194)
      - A Song of the Rolling Earth (Autograph MS, draft outline), Former call number: MS q 193 (Volume MS q 193)
      - Proem These are the sights that I have absorbed in Manhattan Island (Draft outline, draft portions, possibly for use in "Starting from Paumanok"), Former call number: MS q 16 (Volume MS q 16)
      - This Compost (Autograph MS, draft portions), Former call number: MS 13 (Volume MS 13)
      - I know as well as you that Bibles are divine revelations (Autograph MS, draft portions of Who Learns My Lesson Complete? ), Former call number: MS q 5 (Volume MS q 5)
    - Poems Not Appearing in Leaves of Grass
      Listed alphabetically by headings.
      - All Hands Round, Former call number: MS q 24 (Volume MS q 24)
      - I am not content now..., Former call number: II-7C 200 (Box II-7C 200)
      - I am that halfgrown angry boy..., Former call number: MS q 25 (Volume MS q 25)
      - Poem of Existence, Former call number: II-5A 26 (Box II-5A 26)
      - Remembrances I plant American ground with, Former call number: MS 12mo 27 (Volume MS 12mo 27)
      - Scantlings, Former call number: MS q 202 (Volume MS q 202)
      - Thought, Former call number: MS q 28 (Volume MS q 28)
    - Notes for Poems
      - Autograph MSS [Fragments and Ideas for Poems] (Frey's heading), Former call number: MS f 29 (Volume MS f 29)
      - Autograph MSS [Notes for Poems] (Frey's heading), Former call number: MS f 30 (Volume MS f 30)
      - Autograph MSS [Outlines for Poems] (Frey's heading), Former call number: MS f 31 (Volume MS f 31)
      - Autograph MSS [Preliminary Studies for Poems] (Frey's heading), Former call number: MS q 32 (Volume MS q 32)
      - Autograph MSS [Suggestions for Poems] (Frey's heading), Former call number: MS f 33 (Volume MS f 33)
  - Manuscript Prose Subseries, 1852-1891 and undated
    Includes manuscript drafts and revisions of stories, prefaces, essays, lectures, Whitman's commentary on his own literary work and on that by other authors, autobiographical material, and a section of miscellany that consists of notes made on various subjects, the most prominent among them being travel and intellectual history. The fragments in each group are listed alphabetically by headings.
    - Stories
      Listed alphabetically by headings or titles.
      - Distinctness every syllable (Autograph MS, draft portion), Former call number: MS q 191 (Volume MS q 191)
      - Of a summer evening a boy fell asleep (Autograph MS, complete draft), Former call number: MS 56 (Volume MS 56)
      - This singular young man was unnoted for any strong qualities (Autograph MS, complete draft), Former call number: MS f 38 (Volume MS f 38)
    - Prefaces
      - Camden - Phila April 8, '84 (Autograph MS, draft of preface to unpublished edition of Whitman's works), Former call number: MS f 47 (Volume MS f 47)
      - Eidolons Preface Two Rivulets (Autograph MS, draft of preface to Two Rivulets, 1876), Former call number: MS q 62 (Volume MS q 62)
      - For Dem Vistas (Autograph MS, draft of preface to Democratic Vistas ), Former call number: MS 12mo 58 (Volume MS 12mo 58)
      - The name of this tells much of the story... (Autograph MS, draft of preface [?]), Former call number: MS q 63 (Volume MS q 63)
      - (Of the great poet) (Finally) For preface (Autograph MS, draft of introduction to [?]), Former call number: MS q 69 (Volume MS q 69)
      - Struggling steadily to the front... (Autograph MS, draft of prefatory notes to Song of the Exposition, appearing in Two Rivulets ), Former call number: MS 50 (Volume MS 50)
    - Essays, Lectures, and Notes
      - America needs her own poems,... (Autograph MS, possibly a draft of a lecture commenting on 1855 preface to Leaves of Grass ), Former call number: MS 12mo 61 (Volume MS 12mo 61)
      - Canada lecture (Autograph MS, partly published in Diary in Canada, p. 72), Former call number: MS 12mo 60 (Volume MS 12mo 60)
      - for Ottawa lecture (Autograph MS, draft outline), Former call number: MS 57 (Volume MS 57)
      - Founding a new American Religion (? No Religion) (Autograph MS, draft outline), Former call number: MS 64 (Volume MS 64)
      - It is no doubt impossible to say anything not already said... (Autograph MS, draft of a lecture on public education), Former call number: II-5B 42 (Box II-5B 42)
      - It is said, perhaps rather quizzically by one of my friends... (Autograph MS, draft outline of a lecture on Canada), Former call number: MS 65 (Volume MS 65)
      - Italian Singers in America (Autograph MS, draft paragraph on the contralto Alboni), Former call number: MS 66 (Volume MS 66)
      - Materialism (Autograph MS, draft of lecture/essay on evolution), Former call number: MS q 44 (Volume MS q 44)
      - The mob, the trial of Warren Hastings, the death-bed of Robert Burns (Autograph MS, draft portion of an essay on Elias Hicks), Former call number: MS q 36 (Volume MS q 36)
      - The Old World (Europe and Asia) is the region of the poetry of the past (Autograph MS, draft portion of the last paragraph of Shakespeare for America ), Former call number: MS f 37 (Volume MS f 37)
      - Our own account of this poem, 'the German Iliad' (Autograph MS, draft of an essay of the Niebelungenlied and a translation of part of the poem), Former call number: II-5A 41 (Box II-5A 41)
      - ? outset of lecture (Autograph MS, draft outline on preparation for study), Former call number: MS q 45 (Volume MS q 45)
      - Rel. (Autograph MS, draft outline for a lecture on religion), Former call number: II-5A 39 (Box II-5A 39)
      - Sculpture (Autograph MS, lecture/essay on the Greeks), Former call number: MS 48 (Volume MS 48)
      - Slavery - the Slaveholders - The Constitution... (Autograph MS, draft portions of antislavery speeches), Former call number: II-5A 40 (Box II-5A 40)
      - Spring of '59 - read Dante's 'Inferno' (Autograph MS, draft of essay on Dante), Former call number: MS 54 (Volume MS 54)
      - Wants (Autograph MS, draft portions of an essay on labor advertisements), Former call number: MS f 43 (Volume MS f 43)
      - A Word About Tennyson (Autograph MS, printer's copy for Whitman's Tennyson essay in the Critic, Jan. 1, 1887), Former call number: MS q 49 (Volume MS q 49)
    - Notes on Literature
      Listed alphabetically by headings or first lines.
      - [Miscellaneous Notes, Chiefly Literary] (in Frey) (Autograph MSS), Former call number: II-5B 101 (Box II-5B 101)
      - [Notes on Literature] (in Frey) (Autograph MSS), Former call number: II-5B 102 (Box II-5B 102)
      - 1855 - I have looked over Gerald Massey's Poems... (Autograph MS, notes on Massey), Former call number: MS q 73 (Volume MS q 73)
      - But Though so loving, so singing, so dwelling on the past (Autograph MS, fragmentary remarks on a poet, probably Tennyson [in Frey]), Former call number: MS q 99 (Volume MS q 99)
      - Diderot (Dennis Diderot) (Autograph MS, outline of Diderot's career), Former call number: MS 12mo 92 (Volume MS 12mo 92)
      - Dr. Priestly (or Priestley) (Autograph MS, notes on Priestley), Former call number: MS q 74 (Volume MS q 74)
      - Dryden 1631 to 1701 (Autograph MS, impressions of Dryden), Former call number: MS q 72 (Volume MS q 72)
      - Edmund Spenser (Autograph MS, outline of Spencer's career), Former call number: MS 91 (Volume MS 91)
      - Even now Jasmund, the people's poet,... (Autograph MS, notes on Jasmin, Pythagoras, Ossian, Zoroaster, and Greek history and literature), Former call number: MS q 86 (Volume MS q 86)
      - Frances Wright (Autograph MS, notes on Wright's life), Former call number: MS q 76 (Volume MS q 76)
      - Frederick Schlegel 1772 - 1829 (Autograph MS, note on the life and philosophy of Schlegel), Former call number: MS 93 (Volume MS 93)
      - Goethe - from about 1750 to 1832 (Autograph MS, notes on Goethe), Former call number: MS q 80 (Volume MS q 80)
      - Goethe's Complete Works, last complete edition of his own revision (Autograph MS, notes on Goethe), Former call number: MS q 81 (Volume MS q 81)
      - He is a precursor, in some sort of great differences (Autograph MS, notes on Swedenborg), Former call number: MS q 85 (Volume MS q 85)
      - His earliest printed plays 1597 Romeo and Juliet (Autograph MS, notes on the life and work of Shakespeare), Former call number: MS 90 (Volume MS 90)
      - The Iliad, The Bible (? & The Eschylean tragedies) (Autograph MS, notes on the Iliad and the Bible), Former call number: MS 94 (Volume MS 94)
      - J. J. Rousseau (Autograph MS, biographical sketch of Rousseau), Former call number: MS 79 (Volume MS 79)
      - (Jean Paul) Friedrich Richter (Autograph MS, notes on the life and style of Richter), Former call number: MS q 82 (Volume MS q 82)
      - Lafontaine, born about 1621 lived 73 years - (1694) (Autograph MS, notes on Lafontaine's career), Former call number: MS 78 (Volume MS 78)
      - Louis 14th born 1638 - died 1715 Corneille (Autograph MS, notes on the drama of Louis XIV's age), Former call number: MS q 77 (Volume MS q 77)
      - Memory - ... (Autograph MS, notes on the life of Plutarch preceded by a quotation from Locke), Former call number: MS q 84 (Volume MS q 84)
      - The Nibelungen (Autograph MS, notes on the Nibelungenlied, mounted on inside front board of Voices from the Press ), Former call number: III-3 #5 c. 1 (Box III-3 #5 c. 1)
      - Oliver Goldsmith (Autograph MS, biographical sketch of Goldsmith), Former call number: MS 12mo 89 (Volume MS 12mo 89)
      - Shakespeare and Walter Scott (Autograph MS, notes on writing), Former call number: MS 117 (Volume MS 117)
      - Schiller - born 1759 - died 1806 (Autograph MS, notes on Schiller and other German poets), Former call number: MS q 83 (Volume MS q 83)
      - Shelley, born 1792 - died 1822 Keats died 1821 (Autograph MS, notes on Shelley), Former call number: MS q 75 (Volume MS q 75)
      - The Social Contract, Or, Principles of Right (Autograph MS, copy of extracts from a translation of Rousseau), Former call number: MS q 100 (Volume MS q 100)
      - The Song of Hiawatha by H. W. Longfellow (Autograph MS, impressions of Hiawatha ), Former call number: MS 71 (Volume MS 71)
      - Torquato Tasso (Autograph MS, biographical sketch of Tasso), Former call number: MS 12mo 95 (Volume MS 12mo 95)
    - Autobiographical Manuscripts
      - 24 Feb. 1891 In Notes if convenient (Autograph MS, paragraph on his health and publishing, request from Mrs. J. S. Harris for his autograph), Former call number: MS q 132 (Volume MS q 132)
      - (Elan E. Kelsey)... (Autograph MS, notes on Eugene Kelsey, a soldier whom Whitman visited, and on Kelsey's family), Former call number: MS q 130 (Volume MS q 130)
      - How I get around at 60 and take notes (No. 1) (Autograph MS, copy for the first of six articles sent by Whitman to the Critic 1881-1882, published 1881 Jan. 29), Former call number: MS 123 (Volume MS 123)
      - In the Revolution,... (Autograph MS, notes on Whitman's grandfather Kell Van Velsor and his Grandmother Whitman during the Revolutionary War), Former call number: MS 113 (Volume MS 113)
      - Isaac Joseph Stephen Jesse (my grandfather)... (Autograph MSS, notes on various relatives, especially his grandmother Hannah Brush and great aunt Mrs. Sarah Mead), Former call number: MS 120 (Volume MS 120)
      - June 2, '74 (Autograph MS, notes on Dr. Matthew Grier's opinion of Whitman's health), Former call number: MS 122 (Volume MS 122)
      - July 31st 1852 - Mr. Scofield owes W.W. ... (Autograph MS, memoranda written by Whitman when employed as a contractor), Former call number: II-7C 197 (Box II-7C 197)
      - Mother's family lived... (Autograph MS, notes on Whitman's mother's family, 1850), Former call number: MS f 128 (Volume MS f 128)
      - My house and lot 328 Mickle street Camden New Jersey (Autograph MS, draft portion of Whitman's will), Former call number: MS f 133 (Volume MS f 133)
      - Nov. 23rd. 62 Portland av. Jesse Whitman... (Autograph MS, notes on uncles and his father as contractor), Former call number: MS 12mo 104 (Volume MS 12mo 104)
      - Nov. 26 1880 R Worthington... (Autograph MS, notes on pirated edition of Leaves of Grass ), Former call number: MS f 131 (Volume MS f 131)
      - Progenitors (Autograph MS), Former call number: MS 12mo 104a (Volume MS 12mo 104a)
      - Specimen Days (Autograph MS, notes on his parents), Former call number: MS 121 (Volume MS 121)
      - Walter Whitman married... (Autograph MS, notes toward a family genealogy and portion of a diary of Whitman's trip from New Orleans), Former call number: MS f 129 (Volume MS f 129)
        Cf. Richard Maurice Bucke's Biography of Whitman Subseries.
    - Whitman on His Own Writings
      - [Three Autograph MSS] (Notes on nature, a comment on Specimen Days ), Former call number: MS 12mo 116 (Volume MS 12mo 116)
      - '81 'Leaves of Grass' finished (Autograph MS, diary writing on preparation of the 1881-1882 edition for publication), Former call number: MS q 110 (Volume MS q 110)
      - All others have adhered to the principle... (Autograph MS, notes on democracy, poetry), Former call number: MS q 109 (Volume MS q 109)
      - And so I have put those completed poems... (Autograph MS, draft outline), Former call number: MS 108 (Volume MS 108)
      - Current Criticism (Autograph MS, notes on Burroughs's Notes on Walt Whitman ), Former call number: MS 12mo 127 (Volume MS 12mo 127)
      - Feb. 25th '57 Dined with Hector Tyndale (Autograph MS, notes on criticisms of Leaves of Grass made by Whitman's friends), Former call number: MS 124 (Volume MS 124)
      - For criticism L of Grass (Autograph MS, notes on Leaves of Grass ), Former call number: MS 12mo 105 (Volume MS 12mo 105)
      - For Dr. B's Criticism (Autograph MS, notes on Specimen Days ), Former call number: MS 12mo 106 (Volume MS 12mo 106)
      - Friday April 24, '57. True vista before (Autograph MS, notes on education), Former call number: MS 125 (Volume MS 125)
      - Leading Characteristic to unite all sects,... (Autograph MS, notes on religious and social unity), Former call number: II-7C 198 (Box II-7C 198)
      - Make the Works (Autograph MS, notes on writing), Former call number: MS q 204 (Volume MS q 204)
      - May 13 to 26 '81 Down in the Country (Autograph MS, diary entry on preparation of the1881-1882 edition of Leaves of Grass for publication), Former call number: MS 12mo 107 (Volume MS 12mo 107)
      - My Poems, when complete, should be... (Autograph MS, notes on writing poetry), Former call number: MS 126 (Volume MS 126)
      - No I do not choose to write a poem on a lady's sparrow, like Catullus (Autograph MS, notes on Leaves of Grass ), Former call number: MS q 134 (Volume MS q 134)
      - No one of the Themes... (Autograph MS, draft portions of an essay on Leaves of Grass ), Former call number: MS 114 (Volume MS 114)
      - Of William Blake & Walt Whitman (Autograph MS, comparison of Blake and himself), Former call number: II-5B 135 (Box II-5B 135)
      - On the other side is the 'barbaric yawp'... (Autograph MS, draft portion of essay on the differences between Whitman and other poets), Former call number: MS q 206 (Volume MS q 206)
      - Other poets have formed... (Autograph MS, notes on writing poetry), Former call number: MS 115 [display] (Volume MS 115 [display])
      - Put in a passage in some poem... (Autograph MS, notes on translation of his poetry), Former call number: MS q 199 (Volume MS q 199)
      - Rules for Composition (Autograph MS, notes on writing), Former call number: MS q 136 (Volume MS q 136)
      - Sept '81 Copy... (Autograph MS, notes on the publication of the 1881-1882 edition of Leaves of Grass ), Former call number: MS q 137 (Volume MS q 137)
      - Two suggestion points for letter (Autograph MS, two passages of self-criticism), Former call number: MS q 205 (Volume MS q 205)
      - 3 Autograph MSS (Notes on nature, Specimen Days ), Former call number: MS 12mo 116 (Volume MS 12mo 116)
    - Miscellany
      - The Black (The problem of the black) (Autograph MS), Former call number: MS q 192 (Volume MS q 192)
      - Book-learn'g is good... (Autograph MS, notes on education), Former call number: MS 52 (Volume MS 52)
      - Caution (Autograph MS, notes on American literature), Former call number: MS q 196 (Volume MS q 196)
      - Egypt... (Autograph MS, notes on the "development of man" represented by the Egyptians, Hindus, Greeks, Romans, and Hebrews), Former call number: MS 96 (Volume MS 96)
      - Egyptian religion... Greek... Hebrew (Autograph MS, notes on ancient Egyptian and Greek religion and Judaism), Former call number: MS 97 (Volume MS 97)
      - The English Masses (Autograph MS, notes on English people), Former call number: MS 98 (Volume MS 98)
      - His idea of God... (Autograph MS, notes on Emerson), Former call number: MS q 34 (Volume MS q 34)
      - I know well enough that man grows up,... (Autograph MS, notes on "the nature of man"), Former call number: MS f 53 (Volume MS f 53)
      - In metaphysical points,... (Autograph MS, notes on Romantic poetry, education), Former call number: MS 67 (Volume MS 67)
      - It is generally believed in Washington... (Autograph MS, draft portions of a letter on exchange of Civil War prisoners), Former call number: MS 55 (Volume MS 55)
      - It were unworthy a live man to pray or complain (Autograph MS, notes on "whining"), Former call number: MS q 203 (Volume MS q 203)
      - London - 1880 Then about drinking habits (Autograph MS, notes on Canada made during his trip there), Former call number: MS 118 (Volume MS 118)
      - A main part of The greatness of a humanity (Autograph MS, notes on the "evolution of humanity"), Former call number: III-6A (Box III-6A)
      - Of Insanity (Autograph MS, notes on insanity), Former call number: MS q 87 (Volume MS q 87)
      - [Notes on Africa and Asia] (Frey's title) (Autograph MSS, notes on Asia and Africa taken from conversations with travelers and from geography and history books), Former call number: II-5B 103 (Box II-5B 103)
      - [On Poetry] (Frey's heading) (Autograph MS, notes on poetry), Former call number: MS 68 (Volume MS 68)
      - Produce great persons... (Autograph MS), Former call number: MS 51 (Volume MS 51)
      - The RR we go on (Sep 13 '79) from St Louis... (Autograph MS, notes on travels in the U.S. in 1848 and 1879), Former call number: MS q 111 (Volume MS q 111)
      - Specimen Days Oct 31 '84 Presidential Election (Autograph MS, notes for an expanded edition of Leaves of Grass ), Former call number: MS f 46 (Volume MS f 46)
      - Sunday '79 - Took a slow walk... (Autograph MS, notes on New York City), Former call number: MS q 112 (Volume MS q 112)
      - Theological inferences... (Autograph MS, notes on the Bible and its importance in poetry), Former call number: MS q 35 (Volume MS q 35)
      - Visit to NY '78 July 3... (Autograph MS, notes on view of New York from the top of the Tribune building), Former call number: MS 119 (Volume MS 119)
      - Wednesday 4th March... (Autograph MS, notes on the adjournment of Congress, 1863, Mar.), Former call number: MS 12mo 59 (Volume MS 12mo 59)
      - The Whale (Autograph MS, notes on whales), Former call number: MS q 88 (Volume MS q 88)
      - What are inextricable from the British poets are... (Autograph MS, notes on British poets), Former call number: MS q 70 (Volume MS q 70)
  - Proofs Subseries, 1874-1891 and undated
    Proofs of poems and articles published during Whitman's lifetime, some with autograph annotation by Whitman. The dates provided are taken both from the periodicals that carried corrected versions of the articles and poems in proof and also from autograph annotations to the proofs themselves. A mark of "P" next to a date indicates that the proof in question has been dated according to the periodical in which it appeared; a mark of "A," conversely, indicates that the proof has been dated by annotation. Where possible, the titles of the periodicals that published finalized versions of Whitman's articles and poems have been included. Listed alphabetically by title or periodical.
    - A Carol Closing Sixty Nine, undated, Former call number: III-8C, Pr. 10 (Box III-8C, Pr. 10)
    - Colonel Ingersoll's Lecture, Liberty and Literature, 1890 Oct. 21 (A), Former call number: III-8B, Pr. 1 (Box III-8B, Pr. 1)
      Includes a clipping from the New York World from 1890 26 Oct. which reports a conversation between Whitman and Ingersoll.
    - The Dead Carlyle, Boston Literary World, 1881 Feb. 12 (P), Former call number: III-8B, Pr. 2 (Box III-8B, Pr. 2)
    - The Dead Tenor, The Critic, 1884 Nov. 4 (P), Former call number: III-8B, Pr. 3 (Box III-8B, Pr. 3)
    - Death of a Fireman, The New Republic, 1874 Nov. 14 (P), Former call number: III-8B, Pr. 4 (Box III-8B, Pr. 4)